I wanted to ask like regarding like what
we were just sharing about like
recognizing the significance of our
parents like how not recognizing that
um kind of prevent one to be in touch
with like the kind of reality of his
like the kind of reality of his
aggregate say exactly like I wanted to
ask like this specific thing because for
me like it seems like there is like a
link between the two but I cannot really
be pointed very
clearly so so that's where you you would
get to recognize by not denying that
significance you would get to recognize
what the Buddhist says basically when he
says that um if you were to be able to
say may my feeling be like this may it
not be like this then you could say that
feeling yourself but because you can't
have it such that feeling is the way you
want that's how you recognize it feeling
is not self but the thing
is people usually recognize that easily
with displeasure like sure if I'm having
unpleasant emotions or something most
people who practice would see well that
comes on its own but when it comes to
pleasure there's always a tendency
because like as as I always give the
analogy like a pendulum so when you have
been going into sensuality which is
basically all of us and then we go in
the opposite direction you also want to
now deny this stuff with the same
intensity that you were going in the
opposite direction so
then like this this fact that just
pleasure is there by
itself even though you didn't ask for
it that gets to felt as like a problem
like my my parents I shouldn't be
feeling you know that significance
that's clearly there so then I'm going
to cover it up but then how can you
cover something up unless it's there
first mhm like if I say I'm going to
cover cover this thing up it's because I
know it's there so um you basically the
as you said the reality of the
Aggregates is that you have these
feelings and they come and then you have
to recognize so what is there's that um
Gateway where you pass beyond where it
becomes now it's the Aggregates being
there and me delighting on in them on
purpose so that's not going to become
apparent immediately but it is something
that you have to keep in mind always
like I shouldn't think
that these things should stop arising
basically I need
to become imperturbable in regard to
these things that's that's the the right
thing to say so in regard to things with
their full significance which also came
on its own yeah so then the Buddha would
say that's that's why the Buddha would
say uh the the the devel mind is like
when having
seen uh having seen a pleasing form with
the eye he does not Delight in that
pleasing form or having heard a pleasing
sound so it's the pleasure but that's
what people don't recognize like
pleasure is not
in there chance to be this gratuitous
distinction like the pleasure is here in
me I feel the pleasure and then the
object is like out there in the world so
then obviously I have to keep seeing the
object because otherwise I'm dead like
if I don't perceive anything anymore I'm
dead but these feelings that come here I
have to get rid of that part and then
just keep and then you get that's how
you get this notion of bare perception
or the the pure sense data like it's
just the the like the shapes or
something and the sounds waves that you
experience but everything is just like
the void of any feeling but that's
that's not what the Buddha says the the
perceptions and the feelings are there
together you can't separate them from
each other so if you uh like it's not
like the the perceptions are over there
and your feelings are over here all of
it is over there yeah so that feeling is
is more on the side of your parents
being what they are then like you
feeling like that towards them your
responsib posibility is the greed of
virion delusion so are you committing
actions now most importantly you know
through body and speech like they are
your parents but are you killing are you or
parents but are you killing are you or
are you willing to kill steal lie uh you
know do all these sort s sort of unh
wholesome things for the sake of your
parents well that would be now
overstepping the significance of what
your parents are like just on the basic
level um
would you kill someone if they were to
kill your parents or would you even have
harsh harsh speech as as because that's
part of the precepts as well so would
you break any of those things for the
sake of protecting your parents and that
would now be not just the significance
being there but you acting out of it so
then um that extends now to the mental level
um that extends now to the mental level
like once the body and speech is is well
restrained then you can see also have
these thoughts
coming memories or uh Recollections
about my life and all the things that
have happened but I have a choice now to
either as buha said attend to those
things with
your or
without such that the respective defs
will increase but it's not like I have
to get rid of this memory about you know
uh the special significance of my par I
have to make it so that my mind doesn't
kind of start leaping and and get
excited when it sees that but the full
thing you can't deny it because if you
deny it you're basically just trying to
take a shortcut it's like you're
cheating basically it's like you any Act
of the now is secondary upon on the
thing you deny yeah it's like it's like
you have to carry this weight and then
you know your strategy is to like make
it lighter so that you can carry it
instead of make it make yourself strong
so you can lift it up so that's
essentially the thing like whether it's
Pleasant feeling whether it's unpleasant
feeling you don't deny it you see that
it has that weight and you need to be
strong enough to Bear it not make it be
weaker mhm um
so is there kind of something to be said
for the principle behind the bare
awareness it's just a matter of kind of
like you said not trying to shave off
like what
qualifies as well it is bear awareness
like like you know properly speaking uh
right mindfulness would be sort of bare
awareness but the problem is what do you
think is the threshold of baress right
is it excluding anything that's
ignorance exactly so if you're if you
think the bear awareness is just the
sights and the sounds and the and the um
physical Sensations and and all that
stuff because you don't want to be de
dealing with how that feels that's
that's not your bare awareness anymore
because now you're modifying like you're
consciously manipulating The Experience
so that to have to remove the things
that would bother you otherwise right so
that does actually bring up a question
um that's kind of people's
interpretation of the um is it
B in the S just the scene means in in
the Buddha would be he talked about that
in majaya 28 he said
um when there is a when there is when a
sight is seen all the five arates come
into being when a sound is seen all the
five Ares come into being when a when a
smell is smelled all the
so if it were to mean like in the scene
just a scene meaning like no no there's
only a perception and nothing else
that's not what it is it means the scene
is that entirety which includes even the
feeling so then that that's what that
that simil that he gave that in another
like the Mind should be developed such
that it's like a like a big mountain
that even if strong winds come the
mountain doesn't move in the same way
aiku whose's mind has been liberated
even if strong or powerful sights come
into range the mind doesn't move so it's
on the same like yes in the scene just
the scene but that site has a
significance that site has uh the M bait
if you want to call it that way which is
that intensity of either pleasure or
displeasure so you don't you don't
exclude that so it's the the scen in the
sense of like the thing that is seen
could you almost think about it like
that as opposed to like it's not in the
site there is just a sight yeah exactly
it's in like the thing that is seen yeah
so actually that's what the part says it
says um in the scene not just like in the
um in the scene not just like in the
sight it doesn't say in the like the
thing is all these are all kind of
scientific Notions that we have like
sense data and and stimuli but that
that's not how the like you start with
experiences you have experiences that
are made up of form feeling perception
intention and Consciousness you don't
start with you know the be
stuff first and then the feeling comes
kind of added
to if anything the Buddha said feeling
comes first and then perception later
not the other way around but we would
assume that like oh we have feeling we
have the perception first and then you
know if you're not careful enough then
the feelings started to get out of
control no you like would you even be
attending to something if it wasn't
pleasant in the first place like or or
if it or if it was unpleasant let's say
if it was very unpleasant your
perception wouldn't even be directed
towards it basically so it's it's just
uh
obviously it's a matter of just
um to a certain extent recognizing as
you said that oh I am denying this
now and and just continuously because it
comes back again like you see it and
then then you later on you catch
yourself oh wait I'm I'm again falling
into the same thing so that's how you
see if you if you were just assuming
okay so it's about doing this practice
now and I just keep going and that's it
you would fall into that and you just
keep rolling and then uh like it's it's
kind of like you know in a in a race or
something you know you you didn't
actually check if you you know you just run you
check if you you know you just run you
know the the the the Bell didn't even
ring you know you're just
running you know you're just going and
then you reach the end and it's invalid
like you never reach the end because
you're not on the right train just went
somewhere on just kind going around yeah
so so that's but it is that impulse like
yes you want to be free from suffering
but it should not be at the expense of
Rec recognizing uh your attitudes behind
recognizing uh your attitudes behind
that attempt to be free from suffering
like if you try to have it as soon as
possible what what's always going to
happen is you will you will try to cover
it up like if you if if you want to rush
something it's always always like that
like you start making compromises and
you don't you don't see
um the the reality of the foundation in
this case uh is precisely the thing that
you don't want to acknowledge because
seeing those intentions like seeing that
intention to deny things for
example that that's
like that's that dis diss dissonance
that I keep referring to like when you
recognize that and you don't act out of
it
anymore but you don't try to get rid of
it either that's where you start to feel
like oh crap these things are actually
not in my control but people would think
like the the Insight of anata should be
like immediately some kind of release
and pleasure but no the inside of not
that like you're working towards it
right there it's just that it's not it's
not pleasant because it's it's the
opposite of what the Mind wants like
there that perversion of perception that
that the budha talks about yeah so this
is not we're noticing but not trying to
get rid of the
inclination towards covering things up
is what you're saying well even that you
can't get like you need to stop giving
into the inclination right but if you
try to like no no I will never do this
again then you you will basically fall
into again the same same cover up and
and not recognizing that you could still
so you need to remain in that sort of
middle middle ground where you recognize
oh I could fall into this again right
now I am aware of it I'm not giving into
it but it could happen and I can't uh
try to deal with it ASAP like you know
try to try to because that's not how it
works it's like a the Buddha would say
it's that simil of training the the
animals that he would he would bind them
to the to the post and
then he will let them keep pulling it's
not like you know but what what most
people want is no I want the animals to
sit down as soon as possible but that
means they are not actually going to be
tired out you need to let them you know
keep pulling until they actually like
sit down by themselves but if you try to
try to force them to it's just going to
be always that temporary
suppression so on your on your terms in
a way yeah exactly yeah because what are
you using there I mean if we get into
the the fundament that the nitty-gritty
what are you using there to suppress
your your your your senses or your
Aggregates are you using something other
than the senses of the so you're it's
like you're feeding you're feeding like
um like you're you're using one pest to
get rid of another pest it's like you
you're it's like trying to get rid of
the attachment by becoming attached to
the something yeah it's like trying to I
don't know like to erase some like erase
an eraser with
it so so then it's uh you have
the you need to have that recognition
that because some people would say well
no uh you you the practice Begins by
developing the right attachment like you
get attached to your
concentration because people will
recognize clearly there's attachment
here at least they're somewhat self-honest
at least they're somewhat self-honest
but then they would think no no but if I
just keep going that direction later on
like I can then drop the attachment when
I have developed it long enough but the
thing is as said no the the the DH is is
good in the beginning good in the middle
and good in the end in other words at no
point yeah are no at no point are you
justified in having R virion and
delusion if if there is then it's not a
DH y
so it's uh it's like from the start if
there is to to the extent that you are
is to to the extent that you are
not free from things it's because you're
looking at the wrong place so assuming
that some magical thing again not taking
responsibility like some magical thing
will happen and then I would just be
released on account of that rather than
saying no no there is something here
that if I could see it now I would be
freed but it is my own underlying
tendencies that doesn't doesn't allow me
to see it MH not like doesn't allow me
to see it I myself because of the way
that I have inclined my mind it's too
unpleasant to look in the direction of
Nana so I have to basically be uh
dipping my toes into it little by little
because it gets too imparable if I just
get go ahead on so
um yeah it's it it doesn't uh it will
never be like a
sudden kind of
a g yeah a gift from just
chance that that
you and and then that's how you would
have these weird views like oh some
people just get
it from a very young age or something
like you know a child like he yeah they
just got all the luck basically yeah
like the child who could there's that
the boy boy uh who could apparently like
he was he was a meditation Master mhm
when since he was like 5 years old or something